<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A mirrour for monkes written by Lewis Blosius.</title>
            <author>Blois, Louis de, 1506-1566.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 114 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28387</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3203</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24660</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08401796</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08401796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41273</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28387)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41273)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1247:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A mirrour for monkes written by Lewis Blosius.</title>
                  <author>Blois, Louis de, 1506-1566.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>224, [2] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of Speculum monachorum.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Asceticism --  Catholic Church.</term>
               <term>Monastic and religious life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:41273:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41273:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>foreground: two men praying over Jesus's body; background: three crosses on Golgotha</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41273:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41273:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MIRROUR FOR MONKES WRITTEN BY LEWIS BLOSIUS, Abbot of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Benets Order.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device(?) of a sphinx</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at Paris, M.DC.LXXVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:41273:3"/>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:41273:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou deſire of me (beloved Brother Odo) a ſpirituall Mirrour or looking glaſſe, wherin you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould your ſelfe and exactlye ſee both your beauty and, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity: This requeſt of yours is ſomewhat ſtrange: Certaynely I thinke that you knowe me not: for if you did, whence doth it happen, that you requeſt a ſpirituall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41273:4"/>thing of a carnall man: never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe leaſt I might ſeeme to neglect, or rather to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne your requeſt: behould I ſend what our penury hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne able to affourd you Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept therefore of this shorte inſtruction, by reading where of you may peradventure ſlenderly learne what you are, what you are not, or cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynely what you ought to be: firſt and foremoſt therefore I admonish you often and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to conſider the end of your comming into your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery: that being dead to the world and your ſelfe, you may live to God ſtrive therefore with might and may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41273:4"/>to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plish that for which you came learne ſtrongly to deſpiſe all ſenſible things and manfully to breake, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe whole ſomely to for ſake your ſelfe. make haſte to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifye your paſſions and vitious affections that are in you.</p>
               <p>Buſy your ſelfe in repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the inſtable evagations of your heart: ſtrive to overcome wearyneſſe, Idleneſ-and the yerkſomneſſe of your infirme minde: ſpend your dayly labour in thes things, let this be your glorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and healthfull afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Be not remiſſe, but ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe; watch looke about you, and expoſe your ſelfe wholy,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41273:5"/>leaſt your be evilly partiall to your ſelfe: God requireth thus much of you ſoe doth your ſtate.</p>
               <p>You are called a Monke: ſee that you be truly what you are called: Doe the worke of a Monke labour earneſtly in beating downe and caſting forth vice.</p>
               <p>Be alwayes armed againſt the frowardneſſe of nature, againſt the haughtyneſſe of mynde againſt the pleaſures of your flesh, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticements of ſenſuality: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand well what I ſay if you permitt pride, boaſting, vayne glory, ſelfe compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to domineer over your
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41273:5"/>reaſon, you are noe monke.</p>
               <p>If you frowardly followe your owne ſence and dare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe every humble office you are not what you are called you are no monke.</p>
               <p>If aſmuch as in you lyeth you repell not envy, hatred, maliciouſneſſe, indignation: if you reject not rash ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, childish complaynts wicked murmurings, you are noe monke.</p>
               <p>If a contentious and earneſt ſtrife beinge riſen betweene you and another you doe not preſently treat of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliacion and what wrong ſoever hath beene done you doe not preſently pardon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41273:6"/>that but ſeeke for revenge and retayne a voluntary private grudge, and not a true and ſincere affection in your heart, or shew outwardly ſignes of diſaffection, nay if when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion and neceſſity requireth you defer to help him that hath injured you, you are noe monke, you are noe chriſtian, you are abominable before God.</p>
               <p>If having done amiſſe you are ashamed regularly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe your ſelfe, and freely to confeſſe your fault: if being blamed, reproved and correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, you be not patient and humble, you are noe monke.</p>
               <p>If you neglect readily and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41273:6"/>faythfully to obey your ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father if you refuſe to reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and ſincerely to love him as Gods vicar, you are noe monke.</p>
               <p>If you willingly withdraw your ſelfe from the devine of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and other conventuall acts: if you aſſiſt not watchfully and reverently in the ſervice of God, you are noe monke.</p>
               <p>If neglecting internall things you take care only about the externall and with a certaine dry cuſtome move your body, but not your heart to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of religion, you are noe monke.</p>
               <p>If you give not your myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to holy reading and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41273:7"/>ſpirituall exerciſes: if you have your mynde ſoe poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed whith tranſitory matters, that you ſeldome lift your ſelf up to eternall, you are no monke.</p>
               <p>If you deſire delicate and ſuperfluons meates, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperately long after the drinking of wyne beyond the meaſure of a cup, eſpecially if you be in health, and have bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re or other convenient drinke ſufficiently, you are noe mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke.</p>
               <p>If foolishly you require pretious apparell, ſoft beds, and other ſolaces of the flesh, which agree not with your ſtate and profeſſion: if loving
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41273:7"/>corporall reſt you refuſe to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe labour and affliction for Gods ſake, you are noe monke.</p>
               <p>If you cannot endure ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and ſilence but are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with idle ſpeeches, and inordinate laughter, you are no monke.</p>
               <p>If you love to be with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, if you deſire to wander out of the monaſtery through the villages and cittyes, you are no monke.</p>
               <p>If you preſume to take any ſmale matter, to ſend, receave or keepe any things without the knowledge or permiſſion of your ſuperiour, you are noe monke.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:41273:8"/>
               <p>If you eſteeme not the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinations of holy religion though never ſoe litle and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly doe transgres them, you are noe monke: To conclude, if you ſeeke any other thing in the monaſtery, but God and which mighte &amp; mayne aſpire to perfection you are noe monke.</p>
               <p>As I have ſaid therefore, that you may truly be what you are called, and may not weare the habit of a monke in vaine, doe the worke of a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. Arme your ſelfe againſt your ſelfe and aſmuch as in you lyeth overcome and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due your ſelfe if preſently you finde not the peace you deſire
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41273:8"/>if, I ſay as yet you cannot be at reſt, but are troubled and aſſayled by brutish motions and turbulent paſſions: yea if ſoe be, by Gods permiſſion for your owne profitt throughout your whole life you shall have to doe with ſuch ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, diſpaire not, be not ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminately dejected but hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling your ſelfe before God, ſtand and be ſtedfaſt in your pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, and skirmish ſtoutly: for even the veſſell of election, S. Paul endured temptations all his life time, in the which he was buffeted by the Angell of Satan. When he often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeched our lord to be freed from this trouble he obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41273:9"/>it not, for that it was not expedient for him: But our lord anſwered his prayer, my grace is ſufficient for thee, for power is perfected in infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And ſoe afterwards S. Paul did gratefully endure the ſcour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of temptation. Being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted by the example of this moſt ſtrong and invincible champion, fainte not in temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation but endure manfully, remayninge fixt and immovea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in this holy purpoſe. For without doubt, this labour of yours is gratefull to God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſame ſeeme hard and inſufferable to you: goe through this ſpirituall martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with an invincible myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41273:9"/>Doubt not although you be a thouſand times wounded, and as often trod under foote: if you ſtand to it, if you give not grounde to your enemy and like a coward caſt not away your weapons, you shall receave a crowne do according to your ability and commend the reſt to Gods diſpoſing ſaying: As thy will is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo be it done: let the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine will and ordination be your cheife conſolation: which way ſoever you turne your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, where ſoever you are, you shall finde tribulations and temptations as long as this life laſteth: which that you may pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, endure, you ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41273:10"/>wayes to be prepared. But you are happy, if by grace you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve proceeded ſoe farre, that all greife and affliction whats<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oever become truly pleaſing to you for Gods ſake: what thinke you brother, is my glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe bige nough; or is not this yet ſufficient for you but you yet deſire to heare in more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe tearmes, more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly and fully howe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe your ſelfe, within and without, or howe according to reaſon you ought to order every day before God.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:41273:10"/>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:41273:11"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>foreground: three musicians; background: Jesus praying</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41273:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER II,</hi> Howe wee ought to beſtowne our time from our firſt riſing to mattins in the moring.</head>
               <p>AS ſoon as you are wake and ready to riſe to mattens, devoutly arme your ſelfe with the ſigne of the croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, and breifly pray to God, that he will vouchſafe to blot out the ſtaynes of ſinne in you, and be pleaſed to helpe you: Then caſting all vayne imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations out of your mynde thinke upon ſome other thing that is ſpirituall and conceave aſmuch puritye of heart as you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41273:12"/>can, rejoyſing in your ſelfe, that you are called up to the prayſe and worship up of your creatour. But if frailty of body if heavineſſe of ſleepe if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation of ſpirit depreſſe you, be not out of heart, but be comforted and force your ſelfe, overcominge all impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with reaſon and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſuffereth violence and the violent beare it away certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to the labour with you undergoe for the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve of God, ſuch, shalbe your recompenſe and reward, being come of from your bed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and offer your ſelfe both body and ſoule to the moſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41273:12"/>high make haſte to the quire as to a place of refuge, and the garden of ſpiritual delights untill devine office begin, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to keep your mynde in pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and ſimplicity, free from troubles and the multiplicity of uncertaine thoughts collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a godly and ſweete affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards your God by ſincere meditation or prayer. In the perfourmance of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine office have a care to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce and heare the holy wordes reverently, perfectly, thankefully and attentively that you may taſte, that your lord is ſweete, and may feele that the word of God hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible ſweetneſſe and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41273:13"/>power for whatſoever the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt hath dictated is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the life procureing foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and the delightfull ſolace of a chaſt ſober, and humble ſoule remember therfore, to be there faythfully attentive but avoide too vehement co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations and motions of myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, eſpecially, if your head be weake, leaſt being hurt or wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed, confounded and ſtreigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened internally, you shutt the ſanctuary of God againſt your ſelfe: reject likewiſe too troubleſome care, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly bringeth with it puſilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity and reſtlesneſſe, and perſever with a gentle, quiet, and watchfull ſpirit in the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41273:13"/>of God without ſingulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But if you cannot keepe your heart from evagations, be not dejected in mynde: but patiently endevour, patiently doe what lyeth in your power, committing the reſt to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine will. Perſever in your godly affection towards God and even your very defects, which you are noe way able to exclude, will in a manner, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get you conſolation. For as the earth which is of a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient nature, doth by the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of dunge, oſtentimes more fruitfully ſend forth her ſeeds: ſoe a mynde of good will out of the defects which by conſtraint it ſuſteyneth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41273:14"/>shall in due time receave the moſte ſweet fruit of divine vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, if it endure them with patience. And what profitt do you reape by being impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient: doe you not heape cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity upon calamity; doe you not shew your wante of true humility and bewray in your ſelfe a pernitions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety: As long as you do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently aſſiſt, and are ready with a prompt deſire of will to attende, you have ſatified God: neyther will he impute the inordinateneſſe of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtability to you, if ſoe be by your negligence you give not conſent unto it, and before the time of prayer you ſett a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41273:14"/>over your ſences, if you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not offer a perfect dutifulneſſe, offer at leaſt a goodwill: of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a right intent in the ſpirit of humility: and ſoe the devill shall not finde anie occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to cavill againſt you: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you have nothing el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe to offer but a readineſſe, in body and ſpirit to ſerve our lord in holy feare be ſure of it, that you shall not looſe your reward. But woe to your ſoule, if you be negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and remiſſe, and care not to give attendance: for it is writte. Curſed is the man, that doth the worke of God negligently. Be diligent, that you may perfourme what you
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41273:15"/>are able, if you be not able to perfourme what you deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re; upon this ſecurity be not troubled, when impediments happen and you be not able to perfourme aſmuch as you would, when I ſay diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of your ſences, deje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of mynde, dryneſſe of heart greife of head, or any other miſery and temptation afflicted you, beware you ſay not: I am left, our lord hath caſt me away, my duty pleaſeth him not: theſe are words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting the children of diſtruſt endure therefore with a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and joyfull mynde all things for his ſake, that hath called and choſen you firmely
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41273:15"/>beleeving that he is neare to thoſe that are of a contrite heart. For if you humbly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out murmering carry this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den layde on you, not by mortall tongue, to be uttered, what a deale of glory you hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe up for your ſelfe in the life to come. You may truly ſay unto God: As a beaſt am I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with thee: Beleeve me Brother, if being repleat with interne all ſweetneſſe and lifted up abone your ſelfe, you fly up to the third heaven and there converſe with angells, you shall not doe ſoe great a deed as if for Gods ſake you shall affectually endure greife and banishment of heart and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41273:16"/>be conformeable to our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: when, in extreame, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, auginsh feare, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity crying unto his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: lett thy will be do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne: who alſo being thruſt through his hands and feete hanging on the croſſe, had not wheron to leane his head: who alſo moſt lovingly endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thee all the griefes and diſgraces of his moſt bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Therefore in holy lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganimity, conteine your ſelfe, and expect in ſilence untill it shall pleaſe the moſt high to diſpoſe otherwiſe: And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly in that day it shall not be demanded of you hove much intetnall ſweetneſſe you
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41273:16"/>have heere felt: But howe faith full you have bin in the love and ſervice of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:41273:17"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>top: Jesus arrested at night; bottom: a fashionable gathering</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:41273:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER III.</hi> God hath too ſorts of ſervants and the deſcription of both.</head>
               <p>AMonge thoſe that are called the ſervants of God, many ſerve him unfayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, few faithfully indeed unfaithfull ſervants as long as they have ſenſible devotion, and preſent grace of teares, doe ſerve God with alacrity, they pray willingly, joyfully goe about good workes, and ſeeme to live in deepe pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of heart: But aſſone as God hath thought it good to with drawe that devotion, you shall
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41273:18"/>ſee them troubled, chafe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come malicious and impatient and at laſt neyther willing to be att theyr prayers, nor amy other divine exerciſes. And becauſe they feele not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conſolations as they deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, they perniciouſly betake themſelves to thoſe that are externall, and contrary to the ſpirit: where by it is manifeſt, that they are not purely Gods gift, and abuſe them to their owne pleaſure: for if they did love God purely and did not vitioſty reſt in his gifts, they would remaine peaceable in God, thoſe gifts being taken away: and would not even then turneout of the way to unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41273:18"/>conſolations. Therefore they are unfaithfull, becauſe in adverſity they keepe not touch with God. They belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve for a whyle and shrinck bac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke in the time of triall: They would have all things goe on their ſide, and indure nothing that goeth againſt them: if God grant thoſe things that they would have, they ſerve him, if he deny them, they leave him: nay in proſperity they ſerve not God, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And in all things would rather have their owne will done, then Gods they place fanctity, in internall ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and conſolation rather then in the perfect mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41273:19"/>of vices: being ignorant that by the withdrawing of devotion it more certainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth. If one truly love God then by the infuſion of it. For that ſenſible devotion is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly more truly a naturall then ſpirituall devotion. But whatſoever it be, unleſſe a man make uſe of it wiſely, it is wont oftentimes to bring him that is ſoe affected, to a hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den kind of pride, a wicked complacence, and a vaine ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity as wee dayly ſee in the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe unfaithfull ſervants: for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoone as they are tickled with this inward ſweetneſſe, they will for ſooth begin to iudge and deſpiſe others: they thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41273:19"/>themſelves great ſaints, and the ſecretaries of God. They expect and wonderfully long after divine revelations: and wish that ſome miracles were don by them, or of them: by which others might take notice of the holineſſe, which they thinke, they have, but have not. Thus doe they uſe to vanishe away in their owne imaginations, who gape more after ſenſible grace, then the giver of grace: But faithfull ſervants behave themſelves farre otherwiſe for they ſeeke not themſelves, but God: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation, but cheifly the will and honour of God: they alwayes fly proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41273:20"/>whether God be pleaſed to infuſe, or not to infuſe the influence of internall ſweetneſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, they are all one and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in equality of mynde, ceaſe not to love and praiſe God it is not internall dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor difficulty of ſenſes, nor coldneſſe of affections nor drineſſe of heart, nor dejection of mynde, nor drowſineſſe of ſpirit, nor adverſity of tempta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion: to conclude it is neither miſery of adverſity, nor ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of proſperity, that is able to heave them out of their place: for although peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they feele in the inferiour powers of the ſoule the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of inordinate ſorrowe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41273:20"/>proceeding from adverſity, or the violence of ſenſuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light ariſing out of proſperity, they are not for all that deje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: becauſe they continue quiet in the reaſon or higthet parte of the ſoule, and doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their will to the divine will or permiſſion: and grieve that they feele the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction of unſeemely mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Being founded therefo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re as a firme rocke they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte ſtedfaſt in the love of God, as they whoſe cheife comfort is in the wille of God: They are alwayes devour: becauſe with all their power they avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and abhorre whatſoever is diſpleaſing to God, and may
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41273:21"/>never ſoe little contaminate the purity of their heart, and committinge themſelves in all chances to God, doe ſtill poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe a pure free, and quiet mynde. This is the trueſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion and moſt acceptable to God. The other ſenſible devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is more familiare to novices, or thoſe that are lately converted is not durea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſure yet not with ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it is very profitable to us, if wee wiſely make uſe of it: The faithfull ſervants (for ſoe I ſtill call them, whom chriſt calleth not ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, but frineds) faithfull ſervants I ſay, doe ſeeke after that effectuall, and moſt pleaſant ſweetneſſe of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41273:21"/>grace alſo: they ſeeke after the joy of our lords ſalvation: they ſeeke after his moſt love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly countenance, and moſt ſweete embraces: but they doe this with a ſpirituall and bash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, not with a ſenſuall gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, or childish lightnes, or a troubled impatience. They deſire the gift of God, not that they may be ſenſually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in them: but that being made more fervent by them, and more pure from all inordinateneſſe, they may plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe their heavenly bride groo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. They love the gift of God, and willingly thanke him for them: but yet they keepe themſelves as it were
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41273:22"/>quiet and free from them, as long as they reſt not in them. By grace they goe forword to the giver of grace, and ſuprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me good, in whom only it is lawfull for them to reſt: they are truly happy becauſe by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we much the leſſe they ſtick to thoſe gifts they receave ſoe many the more. And although they benever ſoe much indo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed with bleſſings from God, they lift not up their mynde, they diſpiſe not others but themſelves, I ſay, they diſpiſe and acknouwledge themſelves unworthy of all ſpirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, they alwayes keepe in min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that whatſoever they have it is of Gods meere mercy:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41273:22"/>and that of them more is exac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to whome more is given or committed. And ſo contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in holy feare, and by the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe giſts proceeding in humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they confeſſe themſelves to be belowe the loweſt. They rejoice and glory with in them ſelves, if being oppreſt with uniuſt infamy, reproches, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries and uttermoſt ſcorne, they have imitated chriſt: not if they could be elevated abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve themſelves by exceſſe of mynde, or could ſee ſtrange viſions or doe moſt apparant miracles: They preſently ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſigne of croſſe repell the deceitfull ſuggeſtions, by which the devill indevoureth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41273:23"/>to allure them to vaine glory, and ſelfe complacence, noe way conſenting to the ſubtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the wicked ſerpent: they doe not confidently pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the hope of their ſalvation either in the number, or in the merit of good workes which they doo: But put their truſt in the freedome of the ſonnes of God, which they have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned by the blood of chriſt loe then, Brother, knowing the difference of the faithfull and unfaithfull ſervants, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be of thoſe, which may be you are not of, and ſtrive to leave them, of whome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure you are one. If you are of thoſe you would not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41273:23"/>be of, and are not of thoſe of whome you would be, greive and humble your ſelfe for God giveth grace to the humble. And certainly if you humble your ſelfe in the ſight of our lord, greiving that you are yet of the number of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull, you have already in a manner paſſed into the lot of the faithfull; labour, perſever, feare not. You shall not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooved with the unfaithfull, but shalbe receaved with the faithfull. There are others alſo that are bound to the divine ſervice, and yet connot be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed either unfaithfull or faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervants of God: theſe a man may lawfully call the idle
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41273:24"/>ſlaves of the devill. I meane tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe unhappy wretches that eſtee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming either not art all, or very little of devotion, or the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of God, and altogether ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting the interiour parts, make a shew, as though, they honoured God with their lips, but their heart is farre from him, theſe being plunged over head and eares in a ſea of evill, doe little thinke of their owne ſalvation. Theſe are all one to day as they were yeſterday they come from the quire as they went thither viz unclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, tepid apt to noe goodneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, wandring, diſſolute, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout feare; without reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce By the divine praiſes, which
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41273:24"/>with a polluted month they utter, they more exaſperate, then pleaſe God. I would to God theſe, had kept them in the world: for what doe they in monaſteries why tread they on holy ground, why devoure they the almes of the juſt: why pollute they the Angelicall ſchooles of ſpirituall exerciſes with carnall delights. If they intended to live uncleanly, they should have remayned in a place for their purpoſe, and not have entred into places of purity: living negligently in mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naſteries they double the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments of hell, which their ill living in the world had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. But it is out of our
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41273:25"/>way to ſpeake more of theſe things: wherefore I returne whence I ſtrayed.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:41273:25"/>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:41273:26"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>top: Jesus whipped; bottom: people of fashion bathe and groom</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:41273:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER IV.</hi> That for everye howr of the day wee ought to cleave to ſome ſetled exerciſe leaſt our mynde growe ſluggish.</head>
               <p>SOe that you may be ſeted in your private exerciſes preſcribe your ſelfe ſome thing what to doe every howr, and to bee buſied in: But ſoe, that if at any time eyther upon obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience, or any other reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cauſe or chance happening you abbreviate any exerciſe, or wholy overſlip it, you be not inordinately vexed for you ought cheifly to endeavour to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41273:27"/>attayne to this, that in liberty and purity of heart (rejecting all propriety) you may alwayes perſever peaceable, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout trouble before God. For this is acceptable to our lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all other exerciſes bee they never ſoe laborious and hard, whatſoever therefore shall hinder this liberty in you although it be ſpirituall and ſeeme very profitable occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſoe requiring, leave it as much as obedience doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt. Endeavour I ſay, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, all reſtleſneſſe of heart, which choaketh true peace, and perfect truſt in God with all ſpirituall proceedings let not vitious idleneſſe at any ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41273:27"/>take place, for it diſtroieth ſoules. Avoide alſoe idle bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes I meane thoſe that are unprofitable, Neither mervay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le at this kind of ſpeech: let not vitious idleneſſe at anyti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me take place, for there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoe a commendable idleneſſe, which is, when the ſoule fixed on God, and exempted from the noiſe and imagination of all ſenſible things, doth reſt as it were idle in internall ſilence, and in the moſt bleſſed embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cements of her beloved to which if the hand of our lord bring you, you shall profitably and happily be idle otherwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, alwayes either read, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate or praye or take in hand
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41273:28"/>ſomething els, that shall be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and neceſſary and truly if you will ſettle your ſelfe with all diligence to the ſtudy of ſcripture you will be wonder fully comforted and every ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall thing will begin to grow ſweete unto you: and ſoe it will come to paſſe that being accuſtomed to holy delights, you will eaſily contemne thoſe that are carnall: and your myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de will be wonderfully ſtrengh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in your good purpoſe. To the end therfore that you may merit ſoe great a fruit willingly and wiſely give your ſelfe to reading; that is to ſay in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſeeke ſpirituall conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and profitt and the love of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41273:28"/>God, not curioſity, not ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, not neateneſſe and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance of words: for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is not in elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of ſpeech, but in holineſſe of liſe: which elegance of ſpeech nevertheleſſe as it is not overcarefully to be ſought after, if it be wanting: ſoe is it not ſcornfully to be rejected by him that hath it, for it is alſoe the gifte of God. Receave all things with thankes giving and all things shall helpe forward for your ſalvation. How beit be not troubled if many of tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe good things which you hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re or read ſlip out of your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory. For as a veſſell which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41273:29"/>receaveth water remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth cleane although the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter powred in be preſently po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wred out agayne: ſo likewiſe if ſpirituall doctrine often run thorough a well willing myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, although it abide not the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, nevertheleſſe it maketh and keepeth the mynde clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and pleaſing to God. Your cheife profitt conſiſteth not in committing the word of doctrine to memory, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that the effects of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and words remaine in you, that is by this doctrine to get an internall purity, and a ready mynde to fulfill the commandements of God. Lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to apply thoſe things to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41273:29"/>your ſelfe that are ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vice for it is not ſafe to wreſt them againſt others with a fixed indgement of mynde: leaſt while you obſtinately jud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge another, you defile or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your owne conſcience. And ſoe in all things which ſeeme any wayes obſeene avoi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de aſmuch as in you lyeth even the very leaſt allurement of any ſtippery motion if by way of temptation they do impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne, moleſt and trouble you importunately, contradict them with reaſon, deny to gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve conſent, and making the ſigne of the croſſe, direct your whole intention to God: For
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41273:30"/>ſo without hurt you may eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe this danger. Furthermore doe not imitate thoſe that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve noe order in reading, but doe reade what commeth firſt to hande, and where they firſt open the booke: they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke nothing which is not new and ſtrange for they loath all things that are uſvall and ſtale, though never ſoe profitable. farr be ſuch inſtability from you: for it doth not recollect but diſtract the ſpirit: and he is dangerouſly ſicke that is taynted with this diſeaſe: wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly binde your mynde to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of reading and accuſtom your ſelfe to goe thorougth
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41273:30"/>with it, although ſometimes it adminiſter no matter of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Read, I ſay not confuſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or diſorderly but methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally. Repeate thoſe things, againe and againe, that are good. Nevertheleſſe in time of tribulation and ſpirituall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty you may intermitt what your have begun, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your neceſſity turne and apply your ſelfe to other godly exerciſes, which may be more conſolatory. For it is the opinion of the fathers, that it is good to goe to prayer, or meditation from reading, and agayne to have recourſe to reading from prayer: that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41273:31"/>prayer with a commendable viciſſitude ſucceeding reading, and reading ſucceeding prayer, loathſomneſſe may be taken away: and the mynde being as it were fresh and luſty may alwayes be the more able for the propoſed worke, and that the greater fruit may be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of both. And what hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is there why a man should not make short prayers even in reading, and aſpire to God by holy deſires. There are many things that may ſerve either for reading, or prayer or meditation: ſuch are all the ſcriptures in which there is conference with God:
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41273:31"/>Alwayes preferr common prayers before private: and indge them to be more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for you: although ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they may ſeeme more barren and unſavory In like manner eſteeme of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and regular actions for above all things obedience ought to be in the firſt place you: if peradventure you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande in what prayers and meditations you should in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate cheifly exerciſe your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe: if you will credit me, after you have accuſed your ſelfe, and craved perdon for you ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, you shall cheifly beſeech God to mortifie your evill paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41273:32"/>and vitious affections, and quite and cleane to ſtrip you of all inordinateneſſe: and that he will be pleaſed to grant you grace joyfully and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently to endure all tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and temptation. Aske of him profound humility and moſt fervent charity. Beſeech him to vouchſafe alwayes to direct, teach, illuminate, and protect you in all things. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe things in my judgement are moſt neceſſary for you. And indeed they are great and high, neither can they other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be obteyned, then by prayer perſever therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually knocking: and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41273:32"/>doubt our lord will at length open unto you: and will give you aſmuch bread as your neceſſity shall require. But ſoe you neglect not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to give thankes for what you have receaved. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing diſpleaſesh God more, then forgetfulneſſe and ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude for received benefitts. And that you may the more willingly and ſooner incline Gods benignity unto you, pray, attentively for the ſtate of the whole church commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding unto God all the faithfull both alive and dead and every reaſonable creature. Will you further hearein what with pro,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41273:33"/>fitt you may exerciſe your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe. I will tell you: ſinging of pſalmes is profitable, the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditating in other parts of ſcripture is profitable, the conſideration of creatures compared to their creatour is profitable.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:41273:33"/>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:41273:34"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Jesus crowned with thorns; a crowd observes</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:41273:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER V.</hi> Howe powerfull and efficacious the remembrance of Chriſts life and paſſion is.</head>
               <p>ALl prayers, ſinging of hymnes thankeſgiving and holy meditations are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable: But by conſent of all, the remembrance of chriſts hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and eſpecially, of his moſt ſacred paſſion is moſt profitable and only neceſſary, and whorthily. For it is the preſent extermination of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and inordinate affections, a fitt refuge in temptation, and ſureſt ſafegard in dangers a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41273:35"/>ſweete refreshing in diſtreſſe, a freindly reſt from labour, a gentle repreſſing of diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the true dore of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the only entry to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation the ſweet conſolation of the ſoule, the indeficient flame of devine love, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wce of all adverſities, the fountaine of all vertues, from whence they flowe to us, to conclude the abſolute example of all perfection, the haven, hope, truſt, merit, and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all chriſtians, I knew a monke, whoſe cuſtome was to propoſe to himſelfe every day ſome parte of our lords paſſion, as for example: one day he would ſett before his
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41273:35"/>eyes Chriſts being in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. And witherſoever he went that day, wherſoever he chanced to be, if not troubled with any other ſerious and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary cogitation, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he did outwardly, he too<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke a ſpeciall care to direct his internall eye to our lord ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring diverſe diſtreſſes in the garden, and thus would he talke with his ſoule: and my ſoule, behould thy God. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould daughter, attend, ſee and conſider, moſt deare: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould thy God, behould thy Creatour, behould thy father, behould thy redeemer and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: behould thy refuge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould thy defender and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41273:36"/>behould thy hope, truſt, ſtrength, and health. Behould thy ſanctification, purity, and perfection: behould thy helpe, merit and reward: behould thy tranquillity, conſolation, and ſweetnes: behould thy joy, thy delights and thy life: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould thy light, and thy cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne and thy glory: behould thy love, and thy deſire: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould thy treaſure and all thy good: behould thy beginning and thy end: whether art thou ſcattered thou wandring daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. Howe long wilt thou lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve the light and love darkneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. Howe long wilt thou for ſake peace, and involue, thy ſelfe in troubles: Retourne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41273:36"/>thou Sunamite retour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, daugthter, retourne and recollect thy ſelfe moſt deare: leave many things and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce one: for one thing is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for thee. Abide with thy lorde: place thy ſelfe by thy God: goe not from thy maſter: ſitt in his shadow whome thou loveſt, that his fruite may be ſweet to thy throate. It is good for thee to be here daughter. For hither the enemy cannot make his approach, heare are noe ſnares, no dangers, noe darkneſſe. All things are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſafe, all things calme. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide heere willingly moſt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. For heere thou shalt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe and free: thou shalt be
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41273:37"/>merry, and joyfull. Heere are roſes, lillyes and violets: hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re flowers of all vertues doe ſmell moſt pleaſantly. Heere thou shalt ſee a brightneſſe ſweetly inligtning all things with his rayes. Heere thou shalt finde true conſolation: heere thou shalt finde peace and reſt: to conclude heere thou shalt finde all good. With ſuch short ſentences he would both sharply and ſweetly ſpur forward his ſoule, and call her home, when shee was wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring abroad, and force her to apply her ſelfe to the cheifeſt good. Of theſe little ſentences he would take ſometimes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſometimes fewer, ſometimes
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41273:37"/>only one, ſometimes two, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metimes three according to the fervour of his devotion and the pleaſure of the holy Ghoſt: and he would often times ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and repeat them. He would alſo force his ſoule to the remembrance of thoſe things which our ſaviour did and ſuffered for her in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: in the meane time one while exciting her to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of our ſaviours un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable humility, mildneſſe, patience, moſt fervent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible charity ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while to take compaſſion on our lord of infinite majeſty ſoe humbled and afflicted, and then againe to thanke him for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41273:38"/>ſoe great benefitts and piety, an other while to repay love, with love and anon to aske per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don for her ſinnes, and then to beg this or that grace: he would often convert his ſpeech to theſe or the like affectionate and fervent aſpirations: and my ſoule when wilt thou be ready to followe the humility of thy lord when wilt thou imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate his mildeneſſe when shall the example of his patience shyne in thee: when wilt thou be better: when wilt thou be free from paſſions and vitious affections: when shall evill be quite diſtroied in thee: when shall all inordinateneſſe bee blotted out in thee: when wilt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:41273:38"/>thou peaceably and gently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all tribulation and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: when wilt thou perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly love thy God: when wilt thou intimately embrace him: when wilt thou be wholy ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in his love: when wilt thou be pure ſimple and reſiened before him: howe long will it be ere thou be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered no more from his moſt chaſt embracings: and that thou wert immaculate and that thou didſt fervently love thy God. And that thou didſt inſeparably cleave unto thy chifeſt good: And then direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the eye of his heart to heaven, or to the depth of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall light he would frame
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41273:39"/>theſe aſpirations: and my ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, where is thy God: where is thy love where is thy treaſure: where is thy deſire: where is thy totall good when shalt thou ſee him: when shalt thou moſt happily enjoy him when shalt thou freely prayſe him with all the citticens of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: theſe and the like aſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions would he ſecretly ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke either mentally or with his lips taking ſometimes more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metimes fewer according to the internall motion of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt: he would alſo often accuſe his ſoule, that it was too ſlowe, ſtuggish tepid, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratfull, hard, inſenſible, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, miſerable and unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41273:39"/>Againe he would comfort it being dejected with puſilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity or feare, and would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage it with theſe or the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke words: diſpaire not, my ſoule: take comfort daughter, and be confident moſt deare. If thou haſt ſinned, and art woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, behould thy God: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould thy phiſitian is ready to cure thee. He is moſt cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and moſt mercyfull and therefore willing: he is omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent and therefore can par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thy ſinnes in a moment. Peradventure thou art afraid, becauſe he is thy indge: but ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke heart: for he that is thy indge, is alſo thine advocate. He is thy advocate to defend
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41273:40"/>and excuſe thee doing peanan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, he is therefore alſo thy indge to ſave, not to condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne thee being humbled. His mercy is infinitly greater then thy iniquity either is or can be: which words I ſay not, that per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſevering in evill thou should de make thy ſelfe unworthy of his mercy: but that being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from evill thou shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not diſpaire of indulgence and forgiveneſſe thy God is moſt gentle, moſt ſweete, he is wholy amiable, wholy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireable, and wonderfully lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth all things which he hath created: when thou thinkeſt of him, or conceiveſt him in thy memory far be all imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41273:40"/>of terrour, auſterity and bitternes from thee. When we ſay he is terrible, it is not in reſpect of himſelf, but of thoſe, that abuſe his patience and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr to doe peanance. Whoſe moſt bitter and poyſonons ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes as contrairy to his moſt ſweet and pure goodnes he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth and punnisheth; let not thime imperfections diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage thee too much: for thy God doth not diſpiſe thee becauſe thou art imperfect and infirme, but loveth thee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly becauſe you deſireſt and laboureſt to be more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: he will alſo helpe thee if thou perſiſt in thy good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: and will make thee
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41273:41"/>perfecter, yea peradventure, (which thou little hopeſt for) wholy fayer, and every way pleaſing to him. Thus and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable other wayes would he frindly talke with his ſoule, and invite her by chaſt ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to the chaſt love of her beloved: he would alſo turne his ſpeech to our lord and aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to him by holy love would ſay: and good JESU, pious Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ſweet maſter, king of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory, when shall I bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate, and truly humble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee: when shall I truly diſpiſe all ſenſible things for thee: and when shall I perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forſake my ſelfe: when shall I beſtript of all propriety. For
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41273:41"/>vuleſſe there were propriety in me there would not bee ſelfe-will in me: paſſions and inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate affections would have no place in me. I should not ſeeke my ſelfe in any thing propriety only maketh thee impediment and medium bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weene thee and me: propriety only doth hinder thee from me: when therefore shall I caſt of all propriety: when shall I freely reſigne my ſelfe to thy divine pleaſure: when shall I ſerve thee with a cleane, quiet, ſimple, and calme mynde: when shall I perfectly love thee in the armes of my ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le: when shall I love thee with moſt fervent deſire: when shall
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41273:42"/>all my tepidity and imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be ſwallowed up by the immenſity of thy love: and my deſire, my treaſure, ô my to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall good, ô my beginning and end: O my God, ô ſweetneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of my ſoule, ô my conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, my life, my love. O that my ſoule might enjoy thy moſt ſweet embracings: O that were indiſolubly bound with thy lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve: would it were perfectly uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thee. For what is to me in heaven. And beſids thee what would I upon earth. God of my heart and God my portion for ever. When shall the world be ſilent to me, when shall the impediments, troubles, and viciſſitudes of this life ceaſe to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:41273:42"/>me: when shall my pilgrimage be ended: when shall my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journing be conſummate when shall the miſerable captivity of this bannishment be diſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: when shall the shadowe of mortality decreaſe and the day, of eternity draw neare: when shall I lay downe the burden of this body and ſee thee: when shall I praiſe thee with thy ſaints without impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment happily, and eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: O my God, my love, my totall good. He was often wont to uſe ſuch aſpirations kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing that by the exerciſe of them humane ſpirit is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re effectually united to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſpirit and that there by
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41273:43"/>man attayneth the ſooner to the perfect mortification of himſelfe. He had then ready e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where: But if at any time he had more ſufficient leaſure, he would then (ſitting as Mary Magdalen did) rejoyce to lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger more freely and that more to the honour of God, then to the inordinate pleaſing of himſelfe: he would not in the meane time omitt with a certaine internall effuſion of heart, by a ſincere and ſweete affection to adore, bleſſe, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve thankes, and pray: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over tourning his ſpeech to the bleſſed virgin the mother of God, as to a moſt mercifull lady, and moſt liberall ſtewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41273:43"/>of heavenly treaſures, he would ingeminat his pions complaints before her and with an holy importunity ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort a benediction. Another day he would ſert before him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf howe our ſaviour betrayed by Judas was taken and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this point he would iterate his foreſaid exerciſes: and ſo would goe through with the paſſion in order, and having ended would begin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. And about that part of the paſſion, which did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent Chriſt hanging on the croſſe he did not employ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in order and in his proper day, but every day at leaſt breifly, if ſo be he thought it
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41273:44"/>convenient, exciting his ſoule to the earneſt contemplation of theſe things. On every ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of our ſaviour or the bleſſed virgin he would (if he thought it good) propoſe to the eyes of his mynde the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of that feaſt in ſteed of parte of our lords paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which otherwiſe was that day to be frequented: And would performe his internall exerciſes or frindly diſcourſes with his ſoule and about the worke, cauſe, miſtery and joy of that feſtivity. He was alſo much delighted with ſinging the pſalmes. And I knowe, that by the continued cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of this holy exerciſe he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb facs="tcp:41273:44"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:41273:45"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>foreground: man riding chariot; background: Jesus falls under the cross</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:41273:45"/>great conſolation and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler profitt of his labours.</p>
               <p>I vvill ſett downe an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample imitate of it, if you plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. For by this meanes you shall be accuſtomed to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the preſence of God: by this meanes you shall begin to have your ſences ſober, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, exerciſed, and calme: by this meanes you shall prepare your ſelfe away to the higheſt contemplation and perfection: thus whereſoever you are you shall ſpend your time profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: vayne and inſtable cogitati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons being caſte forth out of the corners of your heart and ſuch as are ſerious being entertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in their place: you may
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:41273:46"/>frame your ſelfe meditations and aſpirations in other ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, then wee have, if you perceave the looking in your booke to hinder your mynde, where by you are the leſſe able to reach to God, and to be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, lay a ſide your booke: againe if you perceave it doth further your exerciſe, make uſe of it: for I would that your devotion should be free to you, and that you should follow the grace of the holy Ghoſt without confuſion or anxiety, moreover, by aſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (as you may perceave by the above written coppyes) we underſtand certaine short jaculatory prayers, or burning
<pb facs="tcp:41273:46"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:41273:47"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>foreground: a rich banquet; background: crucified Jesus is offered wine from a sponge</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:41273:47"/>deſires, and lively and amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous affections to God. He that hath not as yet underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the beginning of internall converſation and his owne mortification or hath at leaſt but newly begun, ought not peradventure ſo preciſely to follow this rule.</p>
               <p>But it shall be expedient for him to exerciſe himſelfe for a while according to this manner which I shall opſcribe: lett him therefore every day propoſe to himſelfe ſome part of our ſaviours paſſion and lett him ſtudy to have recourſe in mynde to the ſame whether he ſtand, goe, ſitt, or reſt: unleſſe he have ſome other
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:41273:48"/>profitable or neceſſary thing in his heart to treat of. And lett him often diſcourſe with his ſoule in the preſence of Chriſt ſuffering, either thus, or after the like manner: O my ſoule behould thy God, behould ingratefull, attend thou wretch, conſider thou poore ſoule: behould thy God, behould thy Creatour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer: behould howe the king of eternall glory humbled himſelfe for thee: behould ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we the higheſt majeſty debaſed himſelfe for thee: ſee what ſorrowes, bitterneſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignityes thy ſaviour ſuffereth for thee: Conſider with what charity he loved thee, who
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:41273:48"/>undertooke ſoe great calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and affliction for thee. Ariſe my ſoule, ariſe out of the duſt, ſlip thy head out of the coller thou captive daughter of Sion. Ariſe forſake the pudle of thy vices and leave the vucleaneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of thy negligent life. Howe long wilt thou take pleaſures in perills. Howe long wilt thou eſteeme anxiety and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be reſt: howe long wilt thou ſecurely ſleepe in diſtruction. Howe long wilt thou willingly, leave the right way and wander abroad fart and neere by unknowen pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Returne unto our lord thy God: for he expecteth thee: make haſt, be not ſlacke: for
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41273:49"/>he is ready to receave thee: he will meet thee with open armes: only deferr not thou to returne: Come to JESUS, and he will heate and purifi thee: Joyne thy ſelfe to JESUS, and he will illuminate thee. Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to JESUS, and he will bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and ſave thee: ſometimes lett him more expreſly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid his ſoule of ingratitude and perverſeneſſe, ſaying: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las my ſoule, howe ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full haſt thou bin to thy God: he hath beſtowed innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and moſt admirable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitts on thee, and thou ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paye evill for good: he hath created thee according to his owne image and likeneſſe: he
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:41273:49"/>hath endowed thee with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality: he hath deputed heaven, and earth and all things contayned in them to thy com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modity: he hath enriched thee with many giſts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: he hath brought thee to the light of the Catholique faith: he hath with drawen thee from the dangerous wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves of the world, and conveyed thee to the haven and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a monaſticall life, where thou (as in a moſt ſweete pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice of ſpirituall pleaſures) mighteſt have infinite occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of holy joy and good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes: he hath patiently borne with thee, greviouſly ſinning, and hath preſerved thee from
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:41273:50"/>the jawes of hell. The king hath bin incarnate for thee: thy Creator for thy ſake hath become thy Brother: Neyther did he thinke it ſufficient to be borne for thee: wherefore he would alſo ſuffer for thy ſake, he endured ſorrowe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes, for thy ſake, he was betrayed and taken for thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, he was ſpit on and buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: for thy ſake: he was ſcourged, and wounded with a crowne of thornes: for thy ſake he was ſmytten with a reed, and loaden with the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of the croſſe: for thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke he was nayled to the croſſe and drunke vineger: for thy ſake he wept and shed his moſt
<pb facs="tcp:41273:50"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:41273:51"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>a banquet</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:41273:51"/>holy bloud: for thy ſake he died and was buried. He hath adopted thee to be heire of the kingdome of heaven: he hath promiſed thoſe things unto thee, which neyther eye hath ſeene, nor heart of man can comprehend: But thou haſt left and contemned him who hath bin ſoe many wayes beneficiall to thee thou haſt caſt away the holy feare of him that loved thee: thou haſt shaken of his ſweet ioke, that hath elected thee: thou art become as one of the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Beliall: as an impudent harlot, thou haſt iniquityes, worshipped without modeſty: Thou haſt compacted with
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:41273:52"/>death: Thou haſt given thy hand to the devill: thou haſt bin moſt prompt to all wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: thou haſt heaped evill upon evill, and haſt rejoyced to adde worſe to the worſt. By thy wickedneſſe thou haſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine crucified JESUS-CHRIST, who had choſen thee for his ſpouſe: thou haſt renewed his wounds by thy crimes. Who will give thee grones and ſighs: who will give thee a ſpring of teares, that thou mayeſt night and day bewayle thine ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: O unhappy wretch, what wilt thou doe ò that thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt kept thy ſelfe in the ſtate of innocencie: and that thou haddeſt remayned immacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te:
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:41273:52"/>O that thou haddeſt not miſerably defiled thy ſelfe with dishoneſty: O that thou haddeſt not gone, aſtray from thy God: thou haſt loſt thine innocency thou art defiled, thou art become dishoneſt, thou haſt gone aſtray from thy God: Alas poore wretch and what wilt thou doe: to whome wilt thou fly: from whome wilt thou expect helpe: from whome, but from him, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me thou haſt offended: he is moſte pitifull, moſt courteous moſt mercifull. Humble thy ſelfe, powre out thy ſelfe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke water in his ſight, and he will take pitty on thee: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times lett him turne his lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:41273:53"/>to our lord with theſe or the like words: Alas my lord JESU, what have I done: ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we have I left thee: howe have I diſpiſed thee: howe am I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come forgetfull of thy name: howe have I caſt aſide thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: howe have I caſt aſide thy feare: howe have I trod thy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we under my feete: howe have I traſgreſſed thy precepts. O me, my God, ô me, my Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: O me, my Saviour: O me, my life and my totall good, woe be to me wretched creatu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, woe be to me, woe be to me, becauſe I have ſinned, woe be to me becauſe I have made my ſelfe like to a bruite beaſt, woe be to me becauſe I am become
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:41273:53"/>more ſilly then a sheepe. O good JESU, ô loving sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, ô ſweet maſter helpe me. Sett me on my feete, ſtretch forth thy hand to me being in danger. Cleanſe me from my filth, cure my wounde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme my weakneſſe, ſave me from diſtruction. I confeſſe my ſelfe unworthy to tread on the earth, I am unworthy to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould the light, I am unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of thy aide and grace. For great is myne ingratitude, great, yea too great is the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normity of ſinnes: never the leſſe thy! mercy is infinitly greater: Therefore, ô God, thou lover of mankinde, and my only hope, have mercy on
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:41273:54"/>me according to thy great mercy: and according to the multitude of thy commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions take away myne iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Some times as if he were riſen out of adreame, falling on his knees in the ſight of our lord, lett him affectionately ſay: lord, if thou wilt, thou canſt make me cleane. Or this: O God be propitious to me a ſinner: or that have mercy on me JESUS, ſonne of David: or that other: ô lord helpe me, Soe likewiſe lett him powre forth his heart before the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary the mother of our lord, and all the Saints of God, humbly ſuing for their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:41273:54"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER VI.</hi> We muſt dayly call to munde the manifould ſinnes which we have committed.</head>
               <p>ANd very day, or certayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly very often, when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion shall ſerve lett him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect him ſelfe, and with a profound humility firmely por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſing amendment, lett him call to mynde, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſe before our lord the ſinnes of his fore paſſed life but eſpecially thoſe by which he hath moſt greviouſly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the divine goodneſſe. But it will be indiſcretion to dwell
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:41273:55"/>long upon thoſe that belong to the frailty of the flesh, leaſt the remembrance of them and the longer treating of the ould ſin breed a newe ſin by unlaw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full delight: In which confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, contrition and ſenſible devotion, lett him accuſtome to lament, more that he hath behaved him ſelfs contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lionſly and ingratfully to words his Creator and father, then that he hath brought him ſelfe in danger of eternall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment.</p>
               <p>In the formes of lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and godly complaints which we have preſcribed, he need not care for running over many ſentences: But let him
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:41273:55"/>take which he will, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as he will, obſerving no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if he make choice of only one, or two, or three, which ſoever thy be, he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate againe and againe, he shall doe well. We would that he should doe freely accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his devotion alwayes avoiding confuſion and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity: I knowe one, that being externally; buſied, in his converſion to our lords paſſion among chaſte diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes tooke delight to call to mynde theſe few words, or the like: O good JESU, ô pious Paſtour, ô ſweet Maſter: good JESU, have mercy on me: pious Paſtour direct me: ſweet
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41273:56"/>Maſter teach me: my lord hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe me: Another there was that did take delight torune over ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>metimes more, ſometimes fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the afor ſaid lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and to expreſſe them in diverſity of words recording to his affection. Let our yoing beginner, as I have ſaid, be free in theſe things, and let him ſtirr himſelfe to compunction and diligence in his ſpirituall purpoſe by meditating, if he pleaſe upon death purgatory, judgement, hell and heaven.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>foreground: musicians play for a lady; background: angels</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>foreground: a man with riches and food; background: Thomas puts hands in Jesus's side(?)</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>foreground: man in a luxurious bed; background: priest burns sacrifice on altar(?)</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Nowe after he hath in ſome meaſure reformed the image of God with in himſelfe by healthfull bitterneſſe of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and contrition, he may with greater confidence and profitt imitate the above pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed example of exerciſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore lett him take cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and fervently prepare
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:41273:64"/>himſelfe for a more intimate familiarity with the heavenly briedegroome. But as long as he is weake or colde he shall kindle in himſelfe the fire of divine love by ſerious medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the incarnation or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the only begotten ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of God, ſweetly conferring with his ſoule concerning the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe things. By which medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being once inflamed, let him compoſe himſelfe by prayer and aſpirations, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, by them to unite his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to the cheifeſt good. If he often perſiſt by this meanes to drawe his heart to the love of God, he shall ſoone bring himſelfe to that paſſe, that
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:41273:64"/>preſently at the firſt conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his mynde or aſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without any premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he may be able to ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te himſelfe from creatures and their imagination, and plunge himſelfe in the ſweetneſſe of divine love. Then he shall not ſo much need to remember each, particular ſinne of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe paſt in his penance before God, and with ſorrowe to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the inſight of his heart unto him, for ſoe might his freedome and affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards good be hindred: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let him amorouſly direct his heart to God himſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting whatſoever may ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te or with drawe him from him
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:41273:65"/>neyther do we meane that he should negligently forget his ſinnes: but ſo to remember them, that the remembrance hinder not a greater profitt, therefore lett him confeſſe them dayly to God rather ſummarily then particulerle. Truly we have a more preſent remedy againſt leſſer ſinnes, when we turne to God by a ſweete and effectuall affection of love, then when we tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly biſi our ſelves in the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of them, and ſevere punishment of them. Let him therefore caſt them away into the bottomleſſe depth of Gods divine mercy and goodneſſe, that like a ſparkle of fire in the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:41273:65"/>mideſt of the ſea they may the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re perish. Let him endeavour to reject quite and cleane all inordinate puſillanimity, and ſuperfluons ſcruples of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and perplexed diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence whenſoever they ariſe. For vnleſſe they be preſently lopped of they doe diverſe wayes chooke up the alacrity of the mynde, and very much hinder our internall going for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:41273:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER VII.</hi> Every one ought to conſider his owne ability and to proceede accordingly.</head>
               <p>MOreover let him at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt nothing beyond his ſtrength, but be content with his lott. If he cannot reach as farre as he deſireth, lett him reach as farre as he can: And unleſſe he flatter himſelfe, he may eaſily knowe what pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceedings he is able to make. Nevertheleſſe the devine boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty is liberall, infuſing it ſelfe whereſoever it findeth a myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de worthyly prepared.</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:41273:66"/>
               <p>Wherefore if our ſpirituall practitioner be not yet admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſublimity of contem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plation and perfect charity lett him thinke himſelfe as yet not prepared for the receipt of ſoe great a good. And what good would it doe him to receave that grace, which he knew not howe to make good uſe of. Lett him make haſte to pull up all vice by the roote, that he may be the fitter. But ſtill with this proviſo, that he ſtrive not beyond his ſtrength. Lett him not impatiently try to forerun Gods grace, but humbly to followe it. Lett him not, I ſay, violently force his ſpirit thither, whither he cannot
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:41273:67"/>reach: leaſt preſuming which he ought not, he tumble himſelfe downe headlong by his owne violence, and being crushed be punished for his rashneſſe. Lett him ſoe tend to perfection that unbrideled violence and turbulent ſolicitude beare no part in his indeavours. Lett him attend the meaſure of grace given him, and with all remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that he shall farre more eaſily, ſafely, quickly, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily, attayne to the higheſt degree of contemplation, it is to the comprehending of miſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call divinity, if he be touched and rapt by the meere grace of God, then if he endeavour to attayne unto it by his owne
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:41273:67"/>labours: Lett him alwayes therefore obſerve a meane with diſcretion, leaſt by exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe he rum into defects. The bread of teares is good and many when they should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fresh themſelves ſurfet by it. For they inſiſt ſo long in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and with ſo great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion and agitation, that both ſpirit and body are fayne to lye do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne under the too much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent or extended exerciſe. We confeſſe that many by diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the help of the holy Ghoſt can long and profitably mourne. And there are many agayne that being internally inebriated with the torrent of pleaſure which they take in
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:41273:68"/>God. Do unſeaſonably urge and ſpur forward themſelfes to greater violence, and deſiſt not from this indiſcreet forcing themſelfes, untill being hurt and confounded they fall and faynte in themſelfes, and are thenceforth made unapt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceave the ſweetneſſe of grace. Wherefore the internall heate and violence is alwayes ſoe to be moderated that the ſpirit be not extinguished, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted by it. They whoſe heads are of a good temper, may mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re fervently and ſtrougly inſiſt in fervent aſpirations: but they that have weake heads (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if the weakneſſe growe by indiſcretion are not able to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:41273:68"/>exerciſe themſelfes otherwiſe then very gently and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly. And ſuch can ſcarrely ſomtimes admitt a ſimple com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction of mynde, or medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or reading wihout hurt yea although they leave their heade on ſome place. So great is the calamity that procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of the vice of indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But lett them not diſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, that are brought to that paſſe: But lett them diligently (aſmuch as in them lyeth) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide the diſcommodity of this hurte or confuſion, and humbly pray to God for the reſtoring of that which they have ſpoiled themſelfes. If God be pleaſed to heare them,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:41273:69"/>lett them be thankfull: if not, lett them bleſſe our lord: and for his love learne according to his pleaſure patiently to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure this miſery, which they have done on themſelfes. Lett our internall practitioner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware alſo of all lightneſſe of inconſtancy and inſtability. Lett him take in hand thoſe exerciſes that are good: and lett him goe on with what he hath once begunne, although they like him not: but ſoe that the pleaſure of the holy Ghoſt be followed in all, the decree of his owne will and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being rejected. For the holy Ghoſt doth diverſe wayes as it were invite us and uſe to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:41273:69"/>as bring us by diverſe pathes to that wyne celler and bedcham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of divine love: whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct we muſt ſtill obſearve and moſt readily followe, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide all propriety where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this our ſpirituall ſcoller shall often preſent himſelfe to the holy Ghoſt as a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red inſtrument: and which way ſoever the holy Ghoſt shall bend and apply, lett him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently followe: if att any ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me he shall be drawne or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levated up to the ſoaring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation and embracements of the cheifeſt good, lett him freely offer up himſelfe: and if the paſſion of Chriſt, or any holy meditation and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:41273:70"/>occurre, lett him not ſtay at it, but with all expedition fly thither, whether he is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the ſpirit</p>
               <p>When he dout fully ſtagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in his purpoſe not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing how he ought to procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in his begun enterpriſe, lett him uſe the counſell of men that are prudent, expert, and humble: for ſoe he shall be a greater proficient, then if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying uppon himſelfe he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede according to his owe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions.</p>
               <p>But in the meane time lett him not forget carefully to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve recourſe to the remedy of prayer humbly beſeeching in all things to be directed and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminated
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:41273:70"/>by our lord: leaſt at any time being deceaved he followe error inſteed of truth. And let him alwayes remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, that he can never perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be at leaſure for God, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe his heart be free and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne from all things beſids God: you have nowe heard, Brother, after a manner howe he shold begin and howe he should goe forward in externall exerciſes, that deſireth to attayne to any excellent degree of a pure life. It shall be your parte not only to heare and reade theſe things bu alſo to put them in practiſe. Which if you doe, and have helpe from above, and that you beginne to be cleare with
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:41273:71"/>in, and that pſalmodis and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offices of divine praiſe wax ſweet unto you, ſearch not to high, but be afraide. For although your heart being inlarged you doe awhile run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the way of Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, you have not of your ſelfe inlarged your hearte, but God hath done it. And he that enlarged it can permitt it, his grace being with drawne, to be agayne coupled up and inpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned. The ſunne of juſtice hath shined on you, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſcales being taken of, hath illuminated your mynde: but who can hinder him from hiding himſelfe, of he be ſoe pleaſed. We you therefore
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:41273:71"/>ready: for he will hide himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe and his amiable brightneſſe being once departed, your ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces shall againe be darkned and hindred. Moreover cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine immiſtions by evill an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells will toſſe the shiop of your breſt: yea peradventure the temptation will be ſoe ſtrong, that you will thinke all to oppoſe it ſelfe againſt you. You will ſeeme to your ſelfe to be wholy given over to ſatan: and will not have liſt to open your mouth in Gods praiſe. Neyther shall this calamity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure a little while. Neyther shall you only once or thrice or ſix, or ten times be layed hold on by it, but very often,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:41273:72"/>ſometimes more vehemently then at others. But be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected att this: Neyther thinke any thing ſinniſterly of your faulte. For he hath permitted you to be tempted that it may be manifeſt if you truly love him and that you may learne to pitty, others that are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by temptations. He ſcourgeth and bruſeth you, that he may purge you from vice, and prepare you for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re grace. He ſeemeth to leave you as it were for a time, that you wax not prond, but may alwayes acknowledge that you can do nothing without him: yet nevertheleſſe he doth not forſake you. He exerciſeth
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:41273:72"/>you in theſe, and the like ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities out of the unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble charity where with he loveth you. For the heavenly ſpouſe uſeth this kinde of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation with a fervent ſoule converted unto him. He viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth her ſolemnly in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of her new purpoſe, doth comfort, and illuſtrat her and after he hath recreated and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured her with his ſweete ſmell he draweth her after him and lovingly meeteth her almoſt every where, with his mille feeding his new friud.</p>
               <p>Afterwards he beginneth to adminiſter to her the ſolid foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of affliction, and playnly sheweth her howe much she
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:41273:73"/>ought to endure for his name. Nowe she beginneth to be in a ſea of troubles: men moleſt her without, paſſions trouble her with in: punishments af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict her externally, internally she becommeth dejected by puſillanimity: externally she is greived with infirmities, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally darkneſſe overcaſteth and clowdeth her: the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall parts are oppreſſed, the internall dried up: one while the bridgroome hideth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from the ſoule, another while he diſcovereth himſelfe unto her: Nowe he leaveth her as it were in the darkneſſe and horrour of death, and preſently recalleth her to the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:41273:73"/>ſweetneſſe of light: inſomuch that it may be truly ſaid of him, that he leadeth downe to hell, and bringeth backe againe. By ſuch meanes he tryeth puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, humbleth, teacheth, weanes draws &amp; adorns the ſoule: if he finde her faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all things, and to be of a good will and holy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and that by long ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erciſe and his grace she doth mildly and affectionately en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all tribulations and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, then doth he more perfectly joyne her to himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, and familiarly make her partaker of his ſecrets, and binde her farre otherwiſe to him, then he did at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:41273:74"/>of her converſion: Be not therefore troubled, when ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement temptation ſcourgeth you but as if you receaved a tooken of his love remayne faythfull and invincible in your agonies, ſaying with bleſſed Job: Although he shall kill me, I will truſt in him during this ſtorme it will be ſomewhat hard for you to be preſent at the divine office, by reaſon of the too much inſtability and cloudineſſe of your mynde. Not withſtanding be patient and gently do what lyeth in your power. The night will paſſe away darkneſſe will be diſperſed and light will take place againe. But as long as it
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:41273:74"/>is yet night take heed you be not found idle and negligent: if you have no liſt to pray, ſing, or meditate, then read. If your minde loath reading write, or manfully, exerciſe your ſelfe for the time, in ſome other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall worke, in the meane time diligently rejecting the troubles of vaine cogitations. If drowſineſſe doe unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moleſt you, ſo that it greviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depreſſe you, you shall peradventure (time and place permitting) do better if ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what pertinently to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, leaning your head ſomewhere, you ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a little, then if inexorably you reſiſt it: for if by labour
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:41273:75"/>you thinke to drive it away, as long as you labour you shall be free: But that once paſte, and you betaking your ſelfe to your ſpirituall exerciſes, it will eaſily returne if you ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe lett it not be deepe, nor long: ſoe that it laſt no longer, then one may read one, or two, or three Pſalmes: for ſo your ſpirit being as it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, will ariſe with more expedition and alacrity. They that knowe not howe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves ſoberly in ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, drinking, and the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of their ſences, if thy fly to this remedy, it is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red leaſt they rather aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, then alleviate this diſeaſe:
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:41273:75"/>and falling into a deepe and long ſleepe miſerably looſe their time by ſluggishneſſe: watch carefully againſt thoſe temptations by with the devill endeavoureth to encline the mynde to thoſe things that are indecent and vitious: Be ſure to reject them in the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, before they take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of you with in for unleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe you repell the adverſary at the firſt onſet, if he gett en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, he will preſently clap bolts on your ſoule: and you being deſtitute of liberty and force will hardly be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. But if you have behaved your ſelfe negligently and he fetter you, doe not yeild ſoe,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:41273:76"/>but deny your conſent, and ſtrive againſt him even by cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping on the ground, and pray to our lord in the ſtrength of your ſpirit, that freeing your bonds he will reſtore you to liberty, or at leaſt preſerve you from giving conſent. But knowe that many times you shall more eaſily overcome the adverſary ſuggeſting any filthy impious, and abſurd thing, if you contemne and ſett light by his barking, and ſoe paſſe them over, then if you ſtrive long with him, and with great labour endeavour to ſtop his wicked mouth; But if he over much importune you, and being repelled once or twiſe
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:41273:76"/>do ſtill come on a fresh, you muſt meete with him on play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne termes, that being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne in plaine grounde he may fly away with diſgrace. Nowe he ſetteth on us many wayes: for ſometimes he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to enſnare us ſecretly and under pretence of piety: ſometimes he ſetteth uppon us openly and with open fury: ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metimes he creepeth by little: ſometimes he breaketh forth ſodenly and unlooked for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metimes he layeth ſiege to us by ſpirituall and internall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſometimes by corporall and externall adverſayes or proſperities: wherefore we muſt alwayes have recourſe
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:41273:77"/>to the aide of our lords paſſion, and cry to God with teares. But as I have already ſaid, ſoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re not too high by reaſon of the grace, which peradventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re you have. For what have you, that you have not recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved why doe you glory, as if you had not receaved, take heed therefore that by noe meanes you open the windo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of your heart to the blaſt of vaine glory or the aire of ſelfe complacence: ſee you brag not ſee you boaſte not abroade of what you have receaved: But keepe your ſecret to your ſelfe, let it abide with you: unleſſe you happen to reveale it humbly and modeſtly to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:41273:77"/>intimate and ſecret friend for ſpirituall utility or conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or that you be compelled by obedience, or other mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt neceſſity, or great profitt. See that you beleeve not, that you have receaved the gift of God by your owne merits and labours: but rather judge your ſelfe unworthy (as indeed you are) of all grace and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and worthy of all confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and dereliction. Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re your ſelfe with thoſe that are more holy, that by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of their perfection you may the better acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg your owne imperfection: humble and deject your ſelfe: place your ſelfe unfaynedly
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:41273:78"/>belowe all men: but you will ſay howe can I doe this conſide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring that many with out feare or shame live moſte debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedly which I neyther doe, nor will doe: what shall I caſt my ſelfe belowe them: shall I place them above me: I ſay you shall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER VIII.</hi> A very good meanes to obtayne, humility.</head>
               <p>FOr if you conſider that theſe who to day are ſoe bad, may to morrowe be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re perfect then your ſelfe: and that if they had recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:41273:78"/>the gifts, that are gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you from above, they would leade a farre more holy life then your ſelfe: and that you would ſinne more gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſly then they, if you were not prevented by a more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant grace: I ſay if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe things, you will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily obſerve howe fitt it were, that you should preferr every ſinner before your ſelfe: O if you did knowe the ſecret of God, howe willingly would you give place to others, howe gladly would you take the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt place, howe joyfully would you lay your ſelfe at the feete of others, with what alacrity would you attend the
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:41273:79"/>ſicke, howe devoutly would you honour all, howe affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natly obedient would you be without any delay or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint: But yet I require a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re excellent thing of you, viz that you place your ſelfe not only belowe all men in your heart for Gods ſake, but alſo belowe each creature, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting your ſelfe as moſte ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject duſt, eſteeminge your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe unworthy to tread on the earth, or to enjoy the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitt of light: looke more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly into your ſelfe, howe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull, tepid, unſtable, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and vile you are: and by that meanes you will attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to that moſte humble ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:41273:79"/>of mynde: if the old enemy knocke importunatly at the dore of your heart put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into your conceit that you should thinke your ſelfe ſome body, that you should vainely glory and compare your ſelfe with others: repell the ſubtill villany, locke the dores againſt him: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you feele ſome peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent immiſſions, beware al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes of giving your conſent: for if you conſent, if you let in the impoſtour and incline your mynde to his unlawfull allurements, you have broken your faith and vow, which you have made to the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome of your ſoule: you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:41273:80"/>polluted the bed of your beloved, which before flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed: neyther can you be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his moſt bleſſed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity, unleſſe you caſt out the adulterer, and humble your ſelfe exceedingly. And peradventure you shall not be receaved to favour, unleſſe you be firſt punished and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for a while, and that the filthy kiſſes which the impure ſpirit hath imprinted on your ſoule, be raſed out by the ſcour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of God. But enough hath bin ſpoken of this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:41273:80"/>
               <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>several tombs, surrounded by kings, soldiers, and skeletons</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it la Sagesse du <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> sou l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> de Solom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ci <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it la beaute du <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> sou le no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ci <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it la Riches se du mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de sou le no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Cresus</p>
                  <p>Ci oit la Valleur du monde sou l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dalexandre</p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:41273:83"/>
               <p>Further more beware that while you refresh your body your mynde be not in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne time hungerſtarved. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the mouth of your heart feed on the word of God, and let your eares receave the wholeſome doctrine and deeds of the ſaints: And if you hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to ſitt at that table, where there is noe holy reading, do not thus deprive your ſelfe of her ſpirituall foode; but as much as ſilence will permitt, converſe inwardly either with your ſoule or with God and propoſe to your ſelfe ſome godly thing to keepe your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe doing. As in your dyet, ſoe be alſoe ſober in apparell. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:41273:84"/>ſcorne, and deteſt what ſoever is contrary to monaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſimplicity. Neyther doe you imitate thoſe vaine and wretched monkes, that are ashamed of their eſtate and vocation, but not of their lewd life and converſation: who if they are to goe abroad and to come into the ſight of ſeculars will bewray their foolishneſſe and curioſity: They muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth have ſuch and ſuch clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, and weare their caſſoke after this or that fashion. They are ashamed to weare their apparell according as religion doth ordayne, and according to the conſtitutions of their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours and anceſtors: And
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:41273:84"/>ſoe comming abroade not like humble monkes, but like deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and neate courtiers by this prodigious ſight they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke wiſe men to ſorrowe and indignation, but finde mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of mirth for the devill, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently shewing by this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity what they are with in viz proude, wanton, and full of vaine glory: Alas wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched monkes farre wide from the ſcope of true religion: O monkes not monkes: but mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: ô monkes deteſtable, by being thus deluded by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills cloathing. Is this it, that you promiſed to God, when by the moſt ſacred vowe of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, you ſolemly renounced
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:41273:85"/>the world with all the pompe and vanities there of: is this it, that the king of kings hath taught you by his word: is this it, that he hath shewed by his example, when being wrapt in baſe clouwts, he had noe other cradle then a manger. When likewiſe he was apparelled in a white garment and a purple robe in ſcorne: is this to follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we JESUS: is this to tread in JESUS footeſteeps. O into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable confuſion. O extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of madneſſe. Looke to your ſelfe, brother, that you beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me not like theſe: but rather bee content with plaine appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell whether you be with in the monaſtery or without, For
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:41273:85"/>thus much your profeſſion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceth of you. Every where, but eſpecially during the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne office keepe your eyes from wandring: neyther lightly loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke about you either this way or that, unleſſe neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: leaſt you chance to ſee ſomething, that may hinder you from attention and purity of heart. But although there be noe feare of danger, yet monaſticall dicipline requireth that whether you reſt or goe, you uſe modeſtly to looke do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne upon the ground. Never looke curiouſly on the face of any.</p>
               <p>Let not your gate be too ſwift or haſty eſpecially in the
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:41273:86"/>church, unleſſe it happen that of neceſſity it muſt be ſoe. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the church let it be overſlowe or remiſſe but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and civill: In all things compoſe your ſelfe to a lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble carriage of your whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
               <p>Let your lookes before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be pleaſing with a decent gravity, behaving your ſelfe, courteouſly and affably to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all. And if againſt your will you happen to be over ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, ſoe diſſemble it, that you ſeeme not unpleaſant and harsh, and ſoe be troubleſome to the reſt: when you are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to laugh, laugh ſparingly and like a monke: Avoide lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:41273:86"/>laughter as a great impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to you in your purpoſe, and as the diſtruction of your ſoule: knowing that vehement and immoderate laughter doth violate the cloiſters of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and diſperſing the interiour powers of the ſoule driveth the grace of the holy Ghoſt our of your heart.</p>
               <p>Above all things love ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, ſilence, and taciturnity. Be more ready to heare, then to ſpeake: Be not haſty, nor turbulent, nor clamorons, nor contentious in words: But ſpeake modeſtly bashfully, courteouſly and without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, what is true and right. Be not, I ſay too lowd:
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:41273:87"/>nor yet ſoe lowe that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be underſtood, eſpecially if the place, time, cauſe, or perſon to whom you ſpeake require, that you ſpeake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more lowd then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: for as the voice of a monke should alwayes be bashfull, and for the moſt parte lowe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the holy ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of religion: ſoe alſoe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metimes it ought to be reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable lowde affirme nothing obſtinatly: unleſſe matter of fayth or neceſſity of ſalvation conſtraine: but whoſoever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicteth you, either yeild or hould your peace, if neyther ought to be donne affirme with modeſty and humility
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:41273:87"/>what you knowe to be certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. For by this meanes you shall take away all occaſion of irreligions contention. Lett not your words be biting. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſpeake not any thing that may be either to your owne credit, or anothers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation. But if out of neceſſity or utility you ſpeake any ſuch thing, doe it with a laudable modeſty and a pure intention. Abhorre diſſolute tales as the poyſon of the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. As for jeſts (if they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in your preſence) albeyt you ſuffer them, yet relate them not. Never conſent to a tongue, that ſpeaketh foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unſeemely, and perniciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:41273:88"/>Yea, if ſuch things are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, doe you if it ſeeme good, mildly and with reaſon finde fault with the ſpeaker: if you thinke it not good, yet at leaſt cutt of his ſpeech honeſtly and endeavour to drawe him to bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter diſcourſe: if poſſibly you may give noe eare to back bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. The liberty of externall recreation granted you, either by walking or otherwiſe, ſee you abuſe not: that is, make ſuch uſe of them, that they hinder not your ſpirituall going forward, but rather fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it. You may indeed to the honour of God ſlake your mynde, but let it not looſe: leaſt whileſt you wander abroa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:41273:88"/>being expelled out of your ſelfe, ſome delight or paſſion contrary to the ſpirit, lay hold on you, and diſperſe your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour ſences, and replenish them with bitterneſſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore carefully learne by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine adviſed ſimplicity of min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to abide within your ſelfe: that the noyſe of vaine cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and the motion of inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate affections being repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, you may keepe your heart in ſilence and liberty. Let God be your cheife, yea your who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le thought and ſtudy for it is not enough for you, that he be your whole intention.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe in all externall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupations endeavour, that
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:41273:89"/>with Martha you doe not only for the honour of God perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me your worke prudently, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly, and with alacrity, but that alſo in thoſe workes which you faithfully doe to the honour of God, with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry you direct your mynde being freed from the tumult of cogitations and the confuſed imagination of ſenſible things, to God, or thoſe things that are divine: eſpecially if reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable diſcourſe or any other neceſſity hinder not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:41273:89"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER X.</hi> Martha may ſerve as a mirour for imperfect Religious men; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Magdalen for ſuch as are growne to perfection.</head>
               <p>MArtha becauſe she is diſtracted in her exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall actions and in her right intentions by the multiplicity of vaine cogitations, and is troubled about many things, although peradventure she bee not deformed, yet is she not comely enough. But Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry becauſe she knoweth howe to forſake the troups of unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cogitations, and perſiſting
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:41273:90"/>in unity and tranquillity of mynde doth ſtrive to cleave to goodneſſe it ſelfe, is of more perfect beauty. Wherefore howſoever you are externally occupyed, love not only to be right and innocent with Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha, but alſo to be cleare and ſimple with Mary. Mary hath choſen the better parte which shall not be taken away from her. And you have choſen the ſame: which unleſſe you kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe according to your power, you produce not fruit worthy your profeſſion. Have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alwayes a charitable ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of mynde if you be yet a little one in Chriſt, and are not able to followe Mary ſoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:41273:90"/>ſoe high in mynde: imitate her humility: imitate her affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate watring our lords fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te with teares: imitate her ſweetly feeding on our lords words: imitate her moſt amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſeeking our lord in the ſepulcher. For even in theſe she had ſimplicity of mynde: she loved one thing. She thought on, one thing, she ſought one thing: But imitate her not for your owne delight, but to pleaſe our lord. For if by ſpirituall delectation you doe principally ſeeke your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe in theſe, your ſoule is, not the chaſt ſpowſe of Chriſt, but the moſt baiſe ſervant of ſinne, I might ſay, the divells impure
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:41273:91"/>hackney: you shall at length merit to be admitted to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of higher miſteries by theſe that are more lowe, if I may ſoe call them, which indeed are not lowe, but of a wondrous hight.</p>
               <p>In all things, that differ not from the ſincerity of a monaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call life, conforme your ſelfe to the community, ſtill avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vitious ſingularity: And becauſe you live amonge Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes that live laudably accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſweete auſterity of a holy rule, be not ſingular in abſtinence and watching: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exceede the reſt of the Monkes therein: unleſſe by the revelation of the holy
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:41273:91"/>Ghoſt you knowe it to be the will and pleaſure of God. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther attempt any thing without the counſell and conſent of your ſuperior: leaſt while you preſume of your owne head to afflict your body beyoud mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, you make your ſelfe una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for good workes, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deprive your ſelfe of the fruite of your labour: God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of you purity of myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, not the overthrowe of your body. He would that you should ſubject it to the ſpirit, not that you should oppreſſe it. Therefore as well in exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall exerciſes as internall, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the fervour of your mynde with a holy diſcretion.</p>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:41273:92"/>
               <p>If your will being more ſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we to vertue and remiſſe doe as it were ſleepe, rowſe it up, ſpur it forward. But if having to much bridle, it runne too faſt, repreſſe and cheeke it. Alwayes aſiſt it with holy fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in the preſence of God. And let theſe words alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſounde in the eares of your heart: looke to thy ſelfe. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not over curiouſly the deeds of others, what are their manners and behaviour, unleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe it belong unto you as an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer. Let your curioſity and buſineſſe be about your ſelfe. Howebeyt thinke not in this that I would have you make noe accompt of the exceſſes or
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:41273:92"/>finnes of others, or neglect to amende them aſmuch as in you lyeth, or procure them to bee amended. For we condemne curioſity not holy zeale of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. We diſcommend not what in this caſe is not againſt mature ſtability, or contrary to the ſincere love, of your neighbour. Theſe vices that you ſee in others or heare of them, either thinke them not to be ſimply true, or interpret them in the better parte: but if they be ſoe manifeſt, that no interpretation can qualifie them, endeavour to ſeperate your ſight both of body and mynde from them, and refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting on your owne ſinnes if
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:41273:93"/>you have leaſure, humbly pray to God both for your ſelfe and for them. For ſoe shall you more eaſily avoide unquiet ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picions and rashe judgements: But beware that with conſent of reaſon you rejoyce not at anothers ſinne though of ſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le moment, or of any adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: but mourne for your bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before our lord, calling to mynde that we are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers one of another, all one body, and redeemed all with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me blood. Learne not to be angry, but to pitty the defects of others, and patiently to beare with them, whether they be defects of body or mynde.</p>
               <p>For it is written: beare one
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:41273:93"/>anothers burdens: and ſoe you shall fullfill the lawe of Chriſt. Let not the heavenly grace, with you obſerve in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers excite you to ſatanicall envy, but to a faithfull imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and godly congratulation. And although you have not the ſpirituall good, that you knowe another to be bleſſed with, yet rejoyce in heart that God is honoured by it: as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily thanke our lord for it, as if it were your owne.</p>
               <p>And indeed it will be to your owne good, and you shall be crowned for anothers, as for your owne. Nay more it shall become your owne: ſoe order your mynde, that you deſire
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:41273:94"/>not to pleaſe the world, nor feare to diſpleaſe it. In man al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though very neerly allyed, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve, nothing but good, or the grace and workmanship of good. And agayne hate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but vice.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>skeletons and angels draw death's chariot(?)</figDesc>
                  <p>Le trompe tout le monde</p>
                  <p>Ainsi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> la gloire du <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <p>Nay eſteeme noe man your enemie, but love even your perſecutors, as the moſte dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re furtherers of your ſalvation. What ſoever you ſee, heare, or perceave, in creatures to be delightfull and worthy of ſinguler admiration, either by their naturall diſpoſition, or the art and induſtery of man, referre it to the praiſe of the great Creator, or the uſe of eternall beatitude, that you
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:41273:96"/>may be delighted in our lord. Alwayes be afraide of ſenſuall delectation whenceſoever it have its beginning. For if you ſeeke your ſelfe by that and cleave to it, you will be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled and defiled: utterly deteſt the love of all ſinnes, yea even of the very leaſt. By which not withſtanding, if peradventure being over rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched you fall out of frailty, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict not your ſelfe unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with inordinate puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but humbly confeſſe your fault before our lord: and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing your good purpoſe and piouſly taking heart caſte all your defects into the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable profundity of his
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:41273:96"/>mercies, or his moſte holy wouds. As long as you live in this clay building of your body you may mortifie in your ſelfe the affections of leſſer ſinnes, but wholy avoide to ſlip into them you cannot: godly Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes although thy ſlip ſometi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, yea very often, yet they hate ſinning and beware of it, and greive after they have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. But perverſe Monkes ſinne without hating, without bewayling of it. For they take noe paines to extinguish the affections of leſſer faults nor to avoide the occaſions of them. They deſire the liberty of a more looſe life: they love to be abſent from divine office
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:41273:97"/>and other conventuall acts: they deſire delicate and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous meate and drinke: they eſpie out oportunities of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling: they affect inordinate laughter. They delight in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer buſineſſes, to ſee vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to have curious things for their owne uſe: ſelfe compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, foolish joy, idleneſſe, vaine talke, fables, fantaſtique behaviour, and ſuch other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are with them not at all, or ſcarcely accounted faults: in their conſcience they make no bones of them. For being made inſenſible they thinke themſelves whole, when they are deeply wounded: and the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore neyther care for lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:41273:97"/>their ſinnes, nor amending their life. But what ſay they, theſe ſay they, are noe wounds, or of thy bee, they are very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ones, and as much as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: O wretched Monkes. O mad Monkes: O Monkes, not Monkes. For although they ſeeme little, yet becauſe they are not afraide to receave them, and after receipt of them deferre to cure them, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come mortall: I ſpeake nothing of their falling into pride, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, diſobedience, murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, fury, detractions, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, envy, contempt, glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, with other hideous ſines, and all by this negligence: Doe not, brother, doe not imitate
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:41273:98"/>theſe: for they are not the deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Crucified, and the beloved frinds of God: Neyther ever shall be, unleſſe they leave of to be what they are: looke you better to your ſelfe: leave, remove, caſt aſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de whatſoever may any way hinder you from the true love of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER XI.</hi> Perfect mortification is the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and only short way to perfection.</head>
               <p>BY mortification as by a certaine and compendious way haſten to perfection of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe.
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:41273:98"/>Will you in fewe words knowe what this generality of mortification is. Will you kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we that only certaine shorte cutt. I will tell you I will she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we you: give eare therefore: putt of all propriety: Behould this shorte way: putt of all propriety. And what is the meaning of this: lay aſide all your owne will and ſeeking: put of all the owld man. But that you may the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what is ſpoken, I will propoſe the ſame a little more plainly.</p>
               <p>Have you bounde your ſelfe to the obſervance of poverty. Why then be poore. Poore howe is that: Be poore in the
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:41273:99"/>deſire of wealth, and paſſions of the mynde, poore in ſpirit: if you love and deſire any thing by proprietie of affection and ſenſuality, if as yet you ſeeke your ſelfe in any thing you are yet voluntary, you are not yet truly poore: you cannot yet with S. Peter ſay to God: ſoe we have left all: and have followed thee. Strip your ſelfe, leave all, putt of all propriety whatſoever is not God, let not abide in your heart by cleaving to it, or in ordinately loving it. Be free from all things that are beſids God: in ſoe much that I would have you neyther foolishly to rejoyce for any good newes,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:41273:99"/>nor to be inordinately deje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for any bad: and whether you have not receaved what you yet have not, or have lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, what you have, every way keepe a ſtable and quiet ſtate of mynde for Gods ſake utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny all ſenſible things, yea even your ſelfe. Which is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as to ſay: mortifie in your ſelfe the force of concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſence, delight, anger, and naturall indignation: and aſwell in adverſity as proſperity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne your ſelfe over to Gods divine pleaſure, without any contradiction of will. I have shewed you, that this shorte way and generall mortification of your ſelfe is none other
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:41273:100"/>then the genetall caſting away of all propriety, that is an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation of your ſelfe in all kinds. For indeed perfect humi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lity it ſelfe is that shorte way, by which you goe ſtreight for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the forte of perfection. Nowe this forte, is perfect charity or purity: you will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand howe you may knowe whether you have attayned to that forte. I will give you ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt inſtructions. If alwayes abiding in ſilence of heart as in a moſte quiet haven, you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionatly direct and incline towards God your mynde, being free from all inordinate care, affection and earneſt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of things that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:41273:100"/>you, and in a word from all diſquiet and tumult: ſoe that your memory, your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, your will, that is, your whole ſpirit poſſeſſing the above named forte be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily united to God.</p>
               <p>This is the ſume of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. For although being clothed with this corruptible flesh we cannot alwayes by preſent inſight and memory ſticke to the Theory and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of God: yet here we ought alwayes to be fixed by our intention: and hither as to a marke we ought carefully to recall our mynde, as often as we waſte our ſelfes by unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable light, and unſetled co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations.
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:41273:101"/>As long as by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, meditating, hearing, or ſpeaking we profitably and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely treate of any contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plative and ſpirituall matter, we are not ſeparated from God. Neyther when (occaſion requiring) wee doe with the like ſobriety and ſincerity ſpeake or thinke of externall matters in their due time, doe we goe farre from God. O what a brave philoſopher, what a wiſe man, what an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent devine shall I account you, ô howe happy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, if you convey theſe things by your corporall eares into the eares of your heart, and being ſtirred up to the true
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:41273:101"/>mortification of your ſelfe do lay the axe to the roote of the tree, but what tree is this: it is propriety, of which we ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a little before. But what is the axe then. It is the fervour of ſpirituall and internall exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe. But cheifly the dayly handling of our Lords paſſion, and often aſpirations to God, with prompt obedience and a reaſonable ſobriety of diet are this axe. It is certainly a sharpe axe, a bleſſed axe, a moſte gratefull axe, an axe that bringeth with it all good, and all purity, a golden axe, and deked with pretious ſtones. But the tree is a curſed tree, a tree full of moſte bitter fruite,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:41273:102"/>a tree of all evill, a tree that produceth and nourisheth all inordinateneſſe, a tree of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity and darkeneſſe. This tree is in you, as alſo in all others, and as long as it abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in you, you cannot have perfect light. If therefore you deſire clearly to behold the bright beames of the ſun of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, cutt downe this tree and caſt it from you it is a very thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and hard tree, not to be cutt downe at the firſt blowe, not the firſt day, nor perchance the firſt yeare, no nor perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture in a long time toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: wherefore perſeverance and patience are requiſite. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we as gold, if there be no let,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:41273:102"/>naturally goeth downewards and the flame of fire is carried upwards. Soe the mynde that is purged and purified from the droſſe of propriety and ſeeketh only the will of God, is naturally elevated to her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, which is God and is more freely united to him. But the mynde that is partly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of it, although she tend to her beginning, and be in ſome ſorre illuſtrated from a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bove by the brightneſſe of eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall light: yet notwithſtanding becauſe all impediment is not taken away she cannot have free paſſage nor flowe to, nor be ſwallowed up in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temleſſe depth of eternall
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:41273:103"/>light: that is shee cannot freely be united to God her princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and greateſt good. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more although God out of his bounty be pleaſed ſometimes to lift up ſome to his love by a more eaſy way without many temptations, yet let noe man, although enriched with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall gifts eaſily beleeve, that he hath attayned to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect reſignation of himſelfe, unleſſe in very deed he have endured many moſte grevious adverſities, and have keept a perfect quietneſſe and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of mynde in the tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them. There are many that as long as they feele noe checkes, noe injuries, noe
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:41273:103"/>loſſes, noe temptations, noe troubles, doe ſeeme devout, patient, and humble. But aſſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne as they are but once tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by them, they proudly shew by murmuring, indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and impatience howe litt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le they are mortified. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore before any one can be thought to have attayned to the true abnegation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he muſt neceſſarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure many adverſityes with a voluntary and quiet mynde: And as for him that hath been exactly tryed, by God in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, let him thinke that he hath not yet gone ſoe farre, as that he is able to endure them. For if he had, without
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:41273:104"/>doubt he should not want oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of diverſe tribulations. For God rejoyceth to adorne the ſoule more ſecretly and perfectly joyned to him, with many fold afflictions, as it were with ſoe many pretious pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and ſoe to bring it to the true ſimilitude of JESUS-CHRIST. He therefore that rejecting propriety in all things conformeth his will to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine will and ordination, being equally prepared to undergoe any adverſity, confuſion, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of internall ſweetneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe for Gods ſake, as he would the affluence of any proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, honour, and devotion: he I ſay, that is come to that paſſe,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:41273:104"/>that he can endure all tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and tribulation with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine internall ſweetneſſe and joy, this man hath founde a pretious pearle, this man hath attayned to the higheſt degree of perfection: he is every whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and in all occaſions united to God, and moſt ſweerly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wreth his ſoule to him. He doth purely quietly, ſimply, joyfully, and ſweetly walke all the day long in the light of our Lords countenance, and can adhere to higheſt contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion when he pleaſeth, with the ſame facility that he doth live and breath. What in this vaile of miſery he may receave from heaven and to what God
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:41273:105"/>will be pleaſed familiarly to admitt him, it lyeth not in our power to ſpeake, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are things unſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable. Let him that is ſuch glorifi God, and confeſſe, that JESUS-CHRIST hath rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up the needy from the earth, and lifted up the poore out of the dung, ſithence that of an impure man here on earth he hath made an angell like to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="209" facs="tcp:41273:105"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER XII.</hi> A Monke or Nune by vertue of their profeſſion is bounde to tend, to perfection.</head>
               <p>YOu will peradventure ſay: O this perfection is too much above me: therefore will I not ſtreich my ſelfe, nor endeavour to apprehend it, leaſt I should labour in vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. But my anſwere, is that if you doe according to your words, you are no Monke: For although you are not boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to attaine to perfection, yet are you bounde aſmuch as in you lyeth, to endeavour to
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:41273:106"/>attaine to it. Flatter your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe howe you will: perſwade your ſelfe as you will: faine and pretende what excuſes you will, you are bounde with might and mayne to tend to perfection. It is even ſoe, and noe otherwiſe. If hitherto you have been ignorant of it hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceforth ignorance cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe you, you have bound and obliged your ſelfe, and ſoe you shall remaine.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay, I cannot attaine to ſuch perfection: what meane you by this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt. Are you ignorant that the divine power can doe mo-more, then humane infirmity can imagine. I confeſſe that of
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:41273:106"/>yourſelfe you are not able to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baine it, but God is able to bring you. Beleeve God, hope in God, not in your ſelfe. Truſt in the grace and helpe of God, not in your owne endeavours. Nevertheleſſe that God may be with you, be not you wanting, to your ſelfe by ſloath. Doe what lyeth in your power, putt forth your hands, ſtretch out your armes, confirme your mynde to the deſtruction of vice, to the perfect abnegation of your ſelfe, recollect your heart, produce affection ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate your mynde to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of thoſe things, that are eternall and accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me your ſelfe every where to
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:41273:107"/>attend the preſence of God. Which that you may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter performe, propoſe to your ſelfe according to the above demonſtrated example every day ſome parte of our Lords paſſion, and carefully caſte your internall eye ſight upon the ſame: in the meane time ſweetly converſing with JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS, or with your ſoule, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him. Alwayes I ſay, buſi your cogitations (aſmuch as commodiouſly you may) in ſome divine matter. Lett this be your ſcope, let this be the determination of your mynde: labour for this without reſt with a quiet and pleaſing care. And although every moment
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:41273:107"/>(as I may ſay) you be diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſtray from your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, be not dejected, let not that breed puſillanimitie, but be conſtant, and ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to what you eare reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. By your infatigable la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour you shall overcome all trouble of difficultie. Nay in a little while you will finde this labour more eaſi and pleaſant: and being regenerate to the newneſſe of an unknowen light, you will begin to taſt of the delights laid up for the ſaints, you will not be the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me that you were before: but being happily changed into another man, and clothed with angelicall grace, you will
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:41273:108"/>highly eſteeme what before you diſpiſed, and diſpiſe what before you highly eſteemed: That which before did evilly pleaſe you, will nowe diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe you: what before evilly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed you, will nowe pleaſe you: you will promptly and willingly endure what before ſeemed inſufferable. O plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant metamorphoſis! O chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge proceeding from the right hand of the moſte high. At laſt this laudable cuſtome growing into a ſecond nature, and the divine love more perfectly poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſing you within you will not feele any labour: and as before without labour you did thinke on filthy, impure, abſurd,
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:41273:108"/>foolish, vaine and dreame like things: ſoe nowe you will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout labour adhere to God, and divine things. For of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity the mynde muſt dayly reflect on that, which the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te dearly loveth. Woe, woe unto perverſe, tepid and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Monkes, Monkes in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, but not in life: who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the reverence of their ſtate, and violating their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, are neyther ashamed, nor feare to wallowe in the dirt, and dung of ſloath vanity, and paſſions. But bleſſed yea ten times treple bleſſed are thoſe Monkes and Religious men, who albeit they are of little eſtimation and imperfect,
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:41273:109"/>doe notwithſtanding with might and mayne aſpire and tend to perfection: For they are certainly the adopted ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God: whome our pious Saviour JESUS doth comfort ſaying: feare not little flocke: for it hath pleaſed your father to give you a kingdome: they may ſecurely expect death, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they are yet but in the beginning of their holy purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe: becauſe it shall be pretious in the ſight of our Lord ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may they expect death, and yet not death but the ſleepe of peace, the period of death and the paſſage from death to life. What ſay you, Brother: are you yet in doubt: doe you yet
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:41273:109"/>ſtagger. Take courage I pray you, and being emboldned through ſoe great a confidence in our Lords goodneſſe going on the way of ſalvation wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout feare, preparing your ſoule againſt temptations. Let noe manner of difficulty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright you. In all adverſity, which you happen to endure either at home or abroade, ſay gratefully the will of our lord be done. Although you muſte ſweat much and long, and wreſtle ſtrongly before you can overcome, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant the owld man. Let not that trouble you, conſider not the labour: but the fruite of the labour. Beleeve me, the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernall
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:41273:110"/>piety will be preſent at your labours, and will ſtill moſt lovingly ſuccour you: will comfort you when you feare, will confirme you when you ſtagger, will defend you being aſſayled, will uphold you when you ſlip, will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort you in your ſorrowe, and will nowe and then infuſe the moſte pretious ointment of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſweetneſſe into you. If you perſever, the force of temptations muſt of neceſſity yeild to the force of divine lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve: temptions and tribulations will noe more be grevious and bitter to you, but light and ſweet: then shall you ſee all good and shall finde a Paradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:41273:110"/>even in this life: This I ſay will come to paſſe, if you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſever, and be not of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, that begin well, but being deluded by the allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rements of ſatan, or wearied with the troubles of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and labours, doe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards lightly leave their good purpoſes: They will not be preſſed with the weight of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation And therefore in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of affliction are ſcandalized in our Lord, and going backe from him doe as it were ſeeme to ſay: This ſaying is hard and who can beare it.</p>
               <p>They build not on the firme rocke, but on the unſtable ſand: and therefore their buldings
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:41273:111"/>doe eaſily fall downe at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry puffe of winde, and pushes of the flouds. And would to God they would conſider their ruines: and not ſoe give over: but make haſte to renew the decayed building, noe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re laying their foundation u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſands, but committing them to the firmity of the roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke: Deare brother, if (which God forbid) your building be fallen: renew your overthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne worke: and build againe more happily then you did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. If it fall twice, or ten, or an hundred, yea a thouſand times, or more repaire it as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as it falleth: never diſpaire of Gods mercy: For the innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:41273:111"/>multitude of horrible and hideous ſinnes doth not make God ſoe implacably an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with us, as deſperation alone. For he that deſpayreth of forgiveneſſe denyeth the mercy and omnipotency of God, and blaſphemeth againſt the holy Ghoſt. We cannot be ſoe ready to ſinne, as our lord is to pardon, if we abuſe not his patience: that is, if we will truly, and in time doe penan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce: Thus ought every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to thinke. But leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixity make my treatiſe diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, I thinke it beſt for me to with drawe my pen, and to ſtop the courſe of my begun navigation. In the meane time
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:41273:112"/>while wee take downe our ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, it will not be amiſſe breifly to touch what you ought to doe at every dayes end.</p>
               <p>Every day therefore before you goe to bed, ſeriouſly, but without inordinate diſſipation of mynde, conſider in what you have that day offended: and aske pardon of our moſt mercyfull God, purpoſing thenceforth to live better, and more carefully to avoide all vice. Then pray that he will vouchſafe to keepe you that night from all pollution both of body and mynde, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to him, and to his ſacred Mother, and your holy Angell your ſoule and body to be
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:41273:112"/>guarded and kept. Being gone to bed, arme your ſelfe with the ſigne of our Lords Croſſe: and having honeſtly and chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compoſed your body, ſigh to your beloved, thinking u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſomme good thing, untill ſleepe gently ſeaſe on you. Which if it bee over deepe and rather a burthen then a refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing to your body: if likewiſe by frayle illuſions it procure or produce any thing ſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of dishoneſty, be not over much greived theareat: but humbly ſigh before our Lord: and with humble prayers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech him to grant you ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of diet and ſences, to which ſobriety of ſleepe and purity of
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:41273:113"/>body are commonly compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. This is all deare brother, that I have to ſend you. You deſired a Mirrour or looking glaſſe: ſee whether you have receaved one: If I have any way ſatisfied your deſire, God be prayſed: if not, howe ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver God be praiſed I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, what our Lord hath given me But be they better or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, I deſire you ſometimes to reade them over. Fare you well and pray for me.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:41273:113"/>
            <head>A TABLE Of the thing contained in this treatife.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHapter I. pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. II.</hi> Howe wee ought to beſtowne our time from our firſt riſing to mattins in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. III</hi> God hath two ſorts of ſervants and the deſcription of both. <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. IV.</hi> That for everye howr of the day wee ought to cleave to ſome ſetled exerciſe leaſt our mynde growe ſluggish <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. V.</hi> Howe powerfull and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacious the remembrance of Chriſts life and paſſion is <hi>67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VI.</hi> We muſt dayly call to
<pb facs="tcp:41273:114"/>minde the manifould ſinnes which we have committed. <hi>107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VII.</hi> Every one ought to conſider his owne ability and to proceede accordingly. <hi>130</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VIII.</hi> A very good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to obtayne humility. <hi>154</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. IX. 159</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap X.</hi> Martha may ſerve as Mirour for imperfect Religious men; Mary Magdalen for ſuch us are growne to perfection. <hi>177</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XI.</hi> Perfect mortification is the certaine and only short way to perfection. <hi>194</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XII.</hi> A Monke or Nune by vertue of their profeſſion is bounde to tend, to perfection. <hi>209</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41273:114"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
